Inventory of the Richard Throssel Papers, 1900-1993 (bulk 1902-1933)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
- Photographs and Negatives, 1902-ca. 1920s; Series I.; 14.86 cubic ft. (6 letter boxes, 1 F24 box, 39 negative boxes, 5 shoe boxes and 4 F20 boxes).
  - Lantern Slides, Subseries IV.
    - White Swan - Severely Wounded in the Battle of the Little Big Horn (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1752
    - Two Moons (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1753
    - A Song in the Scalp Dance (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1754
    - Pretty Medicine Pipe (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1755
    - Going to Water (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1756
    - Camp in Winter (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1757
    - Custer Battlefield (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1758
    - The Advance Scouts (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1759
    - In Silent Solitude (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1760
    - Preparing the Sun Pole (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1761
    - Battle Reenactment (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1762
    - Encampment (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1763
    - Sun Dance (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1764
    - Dancers (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1765
    - River Camp (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1766
    - Ceremony (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1767
    - Children Playing Game (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1768
    - People at River (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1769
    - Camp in Winter (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1770
    - Camp in Winter (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1771
    - Boy in Headdress (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1772
    - Sundance Lodge (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1773
    - Outdoor Cooking (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1774
    - Plenty Coups (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1774A
    - Camp at Dusk (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1775
    - Camp at Dusk (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1776
    - Woman Carrying Wood (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1777
    - Rose Bompard Bird (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1778
    - Preparing Hide (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1779
    - Rides a Sorrel Horse (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1780
    - Bead Worker (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1781
    - Camp Scene (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1782
    - Tipi by Leaning Tree (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1783
    - Burial Scaffold (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1784
    - Men in Ceremonial Dress (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1785
      Negative Box 49
    - Dancers (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1786
    - Dancer (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1787
    - Camp at Dusk (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1788
    - Crow Couple in Tipi (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1789
    - Crow Woman (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1790
    - Riders (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1791
    - "Medicine Man - Sitting Bull - Sioux" (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1792
    - "Custer's Last Battle" Painting (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1793
    - Battle Reenactment (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1794
    - Battle Reenactment (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1795
    - The Leaders (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1796
    - Campfire at Night (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1797
    - Chief Gall (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1798
    - Indians in Ceremonial Dress (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1799
    - Foot Race (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1800
    - Riders Fording River (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1801
    - Battle Reenactment (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1802
    - River Camp (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1803
    - Custer Battlefield (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1804
    - Custer Battlefield (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1805
    - Billings Street Scene (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1807
    - Billings Street Scene (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1808
    - Billings Street Scene (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1809
    - Billings Street Scene at Night (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1810
    - Billings Street Scene at Night (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1811
    - Billings Street Scene at Night (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1812
    - Billings Fire Station (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1813
    - Billings Church (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1814
    - Billings Church (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1815
    - Billings Motel Lobby (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1816
    - Billings Lecture Hall (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1817
    - Billings Library (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1818
    - Billings Library (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1818A
    - Billings School Yard with Children (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1819
    - Billings School (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1820
    - Billings School (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1821
    - Billings Home (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1822
    - Billings Railroad Tracks and Houses (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1823
    - Billings Suburb (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1824
    - Billings Factory with Men and Horses in Foreground (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1825
    - Billings Factory with Fire Truck (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1826
    - Farm Overview (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1827
    - Men in Field of Cut Hay (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1828
    - Boy with Tuberculosis (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1829
    - Girl with Tuberculosis - Side Profile (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1830
    - Man and Woman in Poor Living Conditions (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1831
    - Man and Woman in Poor Living Conditions (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1832
    - Fly Leg (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1833
    - Flies (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1834
    - "Suburban Homes Addition - Billings, Montana - Dale-Boyington Agents" - Advertisement (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1835
    - "The Land of the Indian" - Advertisement (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1836
    - "Pictures for Framing" - Advertisement (Box 6, Folder 29)
      TP1837
  - Oversize Glass/Celloid Negatives and Photographs, Subseries V.
    - Bull Goes Hunting (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1838
    - "The Other Medicine" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1839
      Negative Box 50
      2 celluloid negatives 11 x 14
    - Burial Scaffold (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1840
      1 celluloid negative 11 x 14
    - Warriors Crossing River (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1841
    - Indian Camp in Winter (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1842
    - "The Shell Gatherer" - photographic copy of painting (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1843
    - "The Travois" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1844
    - Tipis by River (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1845
    - "Home of the River Crow" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1846
    - "Home of the Mountain Crow" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1847
    - "Song to the Winter Sun" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1848
    - "A Cheyenne Warrior" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1849
    - "The Raiders" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1850
    - Crow Woman (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1851
    - "Crow Tobacco Dance" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1852
    - "Nights Would Find Many Tired People in the Camps" Ookeas Illustration (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1853
    - Plenty Coups (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1854
    - Little Wolf (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1855
      Throssel #614
    - Battle Reenactment (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1856
    - Parade of Indian Horsemen (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1857
    - "The Old Sweat Lodge" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1858
      Negative Box 52
      1 glass negative 11 x 14
    - "Up Pryor Canyon" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1859
    - "Painting the Dancers" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1860
      1 glass negative 14 x 17
    - Tipi (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1861
    - Sunrise on Custer Battlefield (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1862
    - "The Game of Arrows" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1863
    - "The Summer Camp" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1864
    - "Horse Goes Ahead" or "Two Leggings" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1865
      Negative Box 53
    - "The Blacklodge Teepees" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1866
    - "A Song in the Scalp Dance" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1867
    - "The Sentinel" - photographic copy of painting (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1868
    - "The Advance Scouts" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1869
    - "The Last Salute to the Sun Gods" (Box 7, Folder 1)
      TP1870
    - Parade Through Camp (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1871
    - "Blessing of the Foods" (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1872
    - Sunset on Medicine Lodge (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1873
    - "Building the Medicine Lodge" (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1874
    - "Treaty Com. 1879" not a Throssel Print (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1875
    - "A Break in the Circle" - photographic copy of painting (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1876
    - "In the Beartooth Mountains" - photographic copy of painting (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1877
    - "Missed" - photographic copy of painting (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1878
    - "Battle of Royal Elk - An Eight Point Buck Has a 'Royal Head'" - photographic copy of painting (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1879
    - "Coulson 1880" the First Town of Billings, Montana - photographic copy of painting (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1880
    - Indian with Pipe- photographic copy of painting (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1881
      Negative Box 51
    - "Eder's Cabin Before Rebuilt" (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1882
    - "The Lodge" (Box 7, Folder 2)
      TP1883
    - "The Zimmerman Trail" (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1884
    - River Canyon (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1885
    - "Woodbine Falls - Stillwater" (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1886
    - "Upper Lodge Grass Creek" (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1887
    - "East Rosebud" (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1888
    - "East Rosebud" (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1889
    - Men Fishing Near Waterfall (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1890
    - Men Fishing Near Waterfall (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1890A
    - "Clarks Fork of the Yellowstone" (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1891
    - River with Tree Covered Banks (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1892
    - Bridge Crossing Over Stream (Box 7, Folder 3)
      TP1893
    - Lake Covered with Water Lilies (Box 7, Folder 4)
      TP1894
    - Natural Bridge - Yellowstone National Park (Box 7, Folder 4)
      TP1895
    - Lower Falls of the Yellowstone (Box 7, Folder 4)
      TP1896
    - Lower Falls of the Yellowstone (Box 7, Folder 4)
      TP1896A
    - Lower Falls of the Yellowstone (Box 7, Folder 4)
      TP1897
    - Lower Falls of the Yellowstone (Box 7, Folder 4)
      TP1898
    - Grand Canyon of the Yellowstone (Box 7, Folder 4)
      TP1899
    - Tower Falls (Box 7, Folder 5)
      TP1900
    - Old Faithful - photographic copy of painting (Box 7, Folder 5)
      TP1901
    - Grotto Geyser (Box 7, Folder 5)
      TP1902
    - Minerva Terrace (Box 7, Folder 5)
      TP1903
    - Mammoth Hot Springs (Box 7, Folder 5)
      TP1904
    - Liberty Cap (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1905
    - Buffalo Herd (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1906
    - "A Race that is Vanquished" (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1907
    - Bull Elk with Cow Elk (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1908
    - Elk Herd (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1909
    - Elk Herd (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1910
    - Bull Elk (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1911
    - Bull Elk (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1912
    - Antelope (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1913
    - Sheep Herd (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1914
    - "Two Moons" Cheyenne (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1915
    - "White Man Runs Him" (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1916
    - Girl with Dog (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1918
    - Billings Street Scene at Night (Box 7, Folder 6)
      TP1919
- Papers, 1900-1960, 1993; Series II.; .8 cubic ft. (1 document box, 1 slim document box, and 1 folder).
  Includes printed material, correspondence, speeches and miscellaneous items.
  - Books
    - Tomkins, William, Universal Indian Sign Language. Wm. Tomkins, San Diego, California. (digital images are only of the cover and title page), 1926 (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - "The North American Indian" by Edward S. Curtis (outline/introduction to the twenty volume series), 1907 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Catalog, undated; 2 photocopies (Box 56, Folder 2)
    Western Classics from the Land of the Indian #10
  - Correspondence
    - Miss Fannie P. Nye, Throssel Photocraft Co., June 26, 1915 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Richard Throssel, Mother, May 19, 1916 (Box 56, Folder 3)
      (Postcard)
    - Harnois Theater, Throssel Photocraft Co., June, 1928 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - "Westerner", J. Nevin Carson, January 18, 1954 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Henry W. Hough, Erl H. Ellis, March 31, 1954 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Erl H. Ellis, Henry W. Hough, April 7, 1954 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Vera Throssel, Henry W. Hough, December 21, 1955 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Vera Throssel, Mrs. Claude W. Mapes, September 13, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Henry W. Hough, Erl H. Ellis, March 24 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Richard Throssel, Charles Throssel (Brother), undated (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - undated (Box 56, Folder 3)
      (Letter regarding Professor Star)
  - Manuscripts By Richard Throssel, undated (Box 56, Folder 4)
    3 untitled manuscripts pertaining to Indian culture.
    "A Bear Hunt in the Bighorns," 3 pages, typewritten.
    "The Conquest of the Golden West," 11 pages, typewritten.
    "Curly," 3 pages, typewritten.
    "The Face of the Ancient Others," 1 page, typewritten.
    "Folk Lore - White Man Runs Him," 1 page, typewritten.
    "The Honors of a Chief," 5 pages, typewritten.
    "Interview with Two Moons Concerning the Sioux
    Nation, US and Custer and the Battle of the Little Big Horn," 7 pages, typewritten.
    "Naming of Indian Children," 3 pages, typewritten, 2 photos attached.
    "Old Man Coyote and the Whirlwind, A Myth from the Absarokee," 4 pages, typewritten, 2 copies
    "Ookeas, or Little Antelope," 5 different variations, typewritten.
    "Personal," 3 pages, typewritten.
    "Runs the Enemy: Sioux," 4 pages, typewritten.
    "Strife Between Their Medicines," 10 pages, typewritten, 2 copies.
    "Two Moons," 2 pages, typewritten.
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 56, Folder 5)
    Introductory notes on Richard Throssel, corrected copy, 1 page.
    Clipping of picture of bobcat.
    Envelope used for proofs.
    3 pages of Throssel's stationery.
    Clippings describing photographs. "The Advance Scouts"
    "The Advance Scouts"
    "Baby Stuart"
    "Home of the River Crows"
    "The Old Historian - Bull Goes Hunting (Crow)"
    "The Raiders"
    "Sunrise on Custer Battlefield"
    "The Trapper's Home"
    "The Travois"
    "Two Moons - The Cheyenne"
    Hank of human hair.
    Slide of market scene.
    Cutout of photo.
  - Music, undated (Box 56, Folder 6)
    "Forty-Two Studies for Violin," Kreutzer, Rudolphe, 69 pages, cover missing.
    "The Japanese Sandman" Composer: Egan, Whiting.
    "Who?" Composer: Kern, Harback, Hammerstein.
  - Newspaper Clippings
    (More Newspaper Clippings are in Box 58)
    - "Crow Indians to Petition Great White Father for Emancipation," The Billings Gazette, Sunday, August 5,1917; page 2, 2 photocopies. (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - "Death Claims Dick Throssell (sic.)," The Billings Gazette, Sunday, June 11, 1933; Volume XLV #24. (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - "Early Day Violinist Found Billings Lusty, Brawling Infant," Billings Gazette, Sunday, November 2, 1952; Volume 67 #84. (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - The Browning Chief, no volume number, undated; no volume number (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - The Geraldine Review, undated; no volume number (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - "Famous Delineator of Life Among the Indians," no paper title, undated; no volume number. (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - "Graphic Story of Campaign Against Sioux Told by Brig. Gen. E. J. M'Clernand, U.S.A.,", undated; " no paper title, no volume number. (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - "The Land of the Indian" newspaper advertisement, undated; no paper title, no volume number. (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - "Monument Status Sought for Wheel,", undated; no paper title, no volume number. (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - "Work of Noted Indian Artist Shown Here,", undated; no paper title, no volume number. (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - Notes, undated (Box 56, Folder 8)
    1 page regarding history.
    1 page regarding The Game of Arrows.
    4 pages regarding "The Silent Language of the Plains."
    1 page regarding Absarokee books.
    1 page regarding Indian culture.
    1 page regarding Bow and Arrow Fights and the Owl Dance.
    1 page of music to Owl Dance.
    1 page regarding Tribal Ceremonies and Absarokee books.
    1 page regarding Custer Battlefield.
    1 page regarding photo subjects.
    20 pages explaining subjects on lantern slides - first 3 pages missing, photocopy.
    23 pages explaining subjects on lantern slides - photocopy.
  - Pamphlets
    - Dimon, Dr. John "Lewis and Clark Memorial", undated (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - Hough, Henry W. "Richard Throssel Photographer of the Crows,", undated; 2 copies. (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - Throssel, Richard "The Absarokee Books,", 1928; 4 copies. (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - "The Storied Northwest Along the Northern Pacific Railway", 1924 (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - "Twelve Throssel Prints," The Billings Gazette, Billings, Montana, undated (Box 56, Folder 9)
  - Patents
    - Notes on previous patented printing machines, undated; 10 pages. (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - Photographic-Printing Frame patented Oct. 2, 1900, No. 658,839, Charles F. Goddard Jr., 4 pages. (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - Continuous Photoprinting Apparatus patented Mar. 19, 1901, No. 670,349, Lino R. Rondinella, 5 pages. (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - Photographic-Printing Frame patented June 16, 1903, No. 731,102 Gassner F. Fraley, 2 pages. (Box 56, Folder 10)
  - Periodicals
    - The American Rifleman, June, 1933; Vol. 81 #6 (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - Northwestern Motorist, October, 1916; Vol. 1 #5 (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - Out West Magazine, December, 1953.; Vol. XIV #12 (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - Outdoor America, September, 1928; Vol. 7 #2 (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - The Teepee Book, March, 1916; No Volume Number (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - The Teepee Book, 1926; No Volume Number (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - Western Wild Life, July, 1933; Vol. 1 #7, 2 copies (Box 56, Folder 11)
  - Speeches
    - "Curley's Speech,", 1907; 1 page, handwritten (Box 56, Folder 12)
    - "The Wish of Plenty Coos (sic),", undated; 1 page, typed. (Box 56, Folder 12)
    - "Plenty Coups at the Last Council,", undated; 1 page, typed. (Box 56, Folder 12)
    - Speeches by Plenty Coups and Two Moons, undated; 1 page, typed. (Box 56, Folder 12)
    - Memorial for Plenty Coups," By Throssel, undated; 2 pages, typed. (Box 56, Folder 12)
  - Thesis, 1985 (Box 57)
    The Photography Of Richard Throssel: An Annotated Bibliography, Albright, Peggy. Contains original inventory and biography on Richard Throssel.
  - Book, 1993 (Box 57)
    To Image And To See, Crow Indian Photographs by Edward S. Curtis and Richard Throssel 1905-1910 Hood Museum of Art, Dartmouth College, by Tamara Northern and Wendi-Starr Brown, 2 copies.
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 58, Folder 1)
    (More Newspaper Clippings are in Box 56.)
    - The Billings Gazette, Sunday, January 26, 1936; Vol. XLVIII #83. (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - "Pictures by Throssel," The Yellowstone News, Thursday, February 4, 1954; Vol. III #29. (Box 58, Folder 1)
- Non-Photographic Media, 1904-1933; Series III.
  - Aztec Sun God, 1928 (Box 58)
  - Unidentified Woman, undated (Box 58)
  - Rimrocks, undated (Box 58)
    2 hour sketch
  - First Premium Mid Land Empire Fair, 1922 (Box 58)
  - Ocean with Studies in Shadowing, undated (Box 58)
  - Two Advertisements, undated (Box 58)
  - "King of the Mountain", 1923 (Box 61)
  - Indian on Cliff, 1923 (Box 61)
  - "On Montana Prairies", 1923 (Box 61)
  - "Holdup Cut", 1921 (Box 61)
  - Tipi with Woman, 1923 (Box 61)
  - Mountain Lake with Cabin, 1924 (Box 61)
  - "A Mother's Prayer to Heaven", 1904 (Box 61)
  - "The Hour Before the Dawn of Peace", undated (Box 61)
  - "A Break in the Circle" (wolves attacking buffalo), 1922 (Box 61)
  - "The Battle of Royal Elk", 1922 (Box 61)
  - Hawk Attacking a Duck, 1923 (Box 61)
  - "In the Beartooth Mountains", 1922 (Box 61)
  - "Missed", 1921 (Box 61)
  - Wild Cat Attacking Deer, 1923 (Box 61)
  - Medicine Man, 1923 (Art Storage)
  - Man with Pipe, 1919 (Art Storage)
  - Plenty Coups, 1927 (Art Storage)
  - Mountain River, 1923 (Art Storage)
  - Buffalo Hunter, 1933 (Art Storage)
- undated, Series IV. Artifact
  - Artifact - powder horn, undated (Box 59)
    Negative Box